Indiana University Department of History and Philosophy of Science - Chair's records, 1973-1991 C198
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Department of History and Philosophy of Science - Chair's records
1973-1991
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of History and Philosophy of Science
C198
1.7 cubic feet
Collection consists of 1.7 cubic feet of records created by Dept. of History and Philosophy of Science chair Edward Grant. Prof. Grant served as department chair 1973-79 and again 1987-90. The two series, Subject files and Correspondence, provide a wealth of information on the happenings within the department. Included in the Subject files are departmental memos, meeting minutes, and budget information. Frequent correspondents in the Correspondence series are university administrators Kenneth R. R. Gros Louis and Morton Lowengrub.
Access Restrictions
Select files are closed to researchers. These files are marked RESTRICTED in the finding aid.
Access Restrictions
Advance notice required.
Historical Note
The Department of History and Philosophy of Science was established at Indiana University in 1960, largely due to the persistence of Professors Edward Grant and Norwood Russell Hanson. Shortly after Grant came to Indiana University, Hanson approached him with the idea of establishing a program in the History and Philosophy of Science. After garnering the support of other faculty members, a proposal was put forth to the administration, who happily approved the plan. Concerns from the Philosophy Department led to a name change - the Department of History and Logic of Science. The Board of Trustees approved the creation of the new department February 27, 1960.
With four faculty members and nine graduate students, the first year of the Department of History and Logic of Science began the fall of 1960. At the time, the department was primarily a Graduate School program with plans to create a fully-implemented undergraduate curriculum within a few years. The 1960-61 COAS Bulletin states that the intentions of the Department was "to explore, as an independent field of study, the conceptual development of scientific ideas, as well as their integral logical structure." Dr. Hanson served as the first Chair of the department.
A growing department, by the 1963-64 school year, the department had changed its name back to the original Department of History and Philosophy of Science. In the spring of 1964, the department awarded its first degrees - 5 M.A.s, and by the late 1960s, the Ph.Ds the department granted reached record levels, with the peak coming in 1971, with ten Ph.D.s awarded.
From the mid 1970s through the 1980s, class numbers dropped due in part to lack of growth in the field and limited job opportunities. During the 1990s, however, the department experienced a revitalization. The department experienced a substantial revision of its faculty; new hirees brought new perspectives and the department neared its record in the number of Ph.D.'s it granted. In 2000, the department celebrated its 40th anniversary.
Arrangement
Organized in two series: Subject files and Correspondence. Both series are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Scope and Content Note
Collection C198 consists of records created during Edward Grant's tenure as Chair of the Department of History and Philosophy of Science, 1973- 79 and again 1987-90. They were separated from Grant's personal papers deposited at the Archives (Collection C184 - www.indiana.edu/~libarch/Personal/c184pers.html).
The collection is organized in two series - Subject files and Correspondence. The Subject files are arranged alphabetically and wherever possible, Dr. Grant's original file heading was used. The files labeled "Agenda" provide a wealth of information on the department, as Prof. Grant put correspondence, memos, or flyers that needed to be discussed at departmental meetings in these Agenda files. Also prominent in the collection are the Budget files, which hold correspondence, Dr. Grant's figures, and memos. Some files are are not open to researchers, as they contain evaluations or letters of recommendation. These files are indicated (RESTRICTED) and listed where they would fall alphabetically, but then placed at the end of Box 2.
The Correspondence series is arranged alphabetically and the more frequent correspondents were assigned their own folders. Frequent correspondents include university administrators Kenneth R. R. Gros-Louis and Morton Lowengrub.
Acquisition Information
Accession # 98/038, 98/028
Departmental chairmen (Universities) --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Departmental chairmen (Universities) --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Correspondence; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Lowengrub, Morton, 1935- -- Correspondence; Lowengrub, Morton, 1935- -- Correspondence -- Selections; Gros Louis, Kenneth R. R., 1936-2017 -- Correspondence; Gros Louis, Kenneth R. R., 1936-2017 -- Correspondence -- Selections
- Subject files, 1973-1991
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 11 restricted folders. Research is closed in these folders. Please contact the University Archivist for further information.
  - Agenda (Agenda items for Dept. meetings), 1987-1988; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Agenda, Fall 1988 (Box 1)
  - Agenda, Spring 1989 (Box 1)
  - Agendas, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Applicants to HPS, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Associate Instructors (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Fall 1989 (Box 1)
  - Associate Instructors budget, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Associate Instructor letters (Student aid, work-study, etc.), 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Budget (Box 1)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Budget conference (Box 1)
    - March 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Outline for Budget conference, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Carmichael, Ann (Box 1)
    - - Review, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - - Tenure, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Chair replacements, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Coffa, J. Alberto - Promotion committee report, c. 1983 (Box 1)
  - College of Arts and Sciences - (Box 1)
    General
    Departmental comparisons of credit hours completed, undergraduate majors and graduate majors, 1973-1974 through 1977-1978 academic years
  - College of Arts and Sciences salary process, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Computer plan, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Course descriptions, Fall 1978 (Box 1)
  - Courses, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Criteria for evidence of departmental merit, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Cronin, James - Patten Foundation lecturer nomination, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Daley, Thomas E. - Evaluation, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Dean's report to the Arts and Sciences faculty, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Department meetings (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - Spring, 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Department meeting minutes, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Dordick, Rowan - Dissertation proposal, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Equipment and budget, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Faculty hiring, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Freshman seminars, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Giere, Ronald - Salary grievance, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Goodbody Gazette, Fall 1990 (Box 1)
  - Graduate school fellowships - policy and rules, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Harder, Allen - Thesis proposal, undated (Box 1)
  - Halporn, Barbara - Dissertation proposal, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Harris, Karine and Steve - Visit, 1990 (Box 1)
  - History of Medicine course, 1974-1978; undated (Box 1)
  - HPS annual report, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - HPS brochure, undated (Box 1)
  - HPS Department-Course evaluation, undated (Box 1)
  - HPS Executive committee election, undated (Box 1)
  - HPS faculty, 1988 (Box 1)
  - HPS faculty: CVs and faculty annual reports, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - HPS faculty information, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - HPS job descriptions and personnel, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - HPS jobs for (vacancy announcement), 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - HPS - new student biographies, 1984-1985; undated (Box 1)
  - HPS Theme song by Warren Van Egmond, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Indiana University - Bloomington - Equity review - women and minorities, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - IU Foundation account, undated (Box 1)
  - Institute for the Comparative Study of the History and Philosophy of Science and Technology (Box 1)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - - Proposal, undated (Box 1)
  - Report of the Internal Review Committee for HPS, 1984 (Box 1)
  - International Center for Advanced Study in History and Philosophy of Science, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Lecture announcements, 1978-1979; undated (Box 1)
  - Lilly materials (Professorships and lecture series), 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Long range plan - College of Arts and Sciences, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Long range plan for Department of History and Philosophy of Science, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Malaysia Cooperative program - Applicants, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Memos (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Memos to and from Deans (Box 1)
    - 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Memos to colleagues, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1987; undated (Box 1)
  - North, John - College professorship, 1986-1990 (Box 1)
  - Outside minor requirements in History and Philosophy of Science for Ph.D. requirements, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Quality report, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Recruitment (Box 2)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Report of COAS -, Jan. 28, 1990 (Box 2)
    (Items, reports pulled together for Dept. annual report)
  - Report from DHPS Merit Committee on Chair's salary, undated (Box 2)
  - Request for seminar proposals for partial Sigma Xi support, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Research and Graduate development, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Sageng, Eric - Research proposal, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Salary material, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Sawyer, Charlie - visit, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Secretary problem, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Shixiong, Sun, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Joel and Susan, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Space problems, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Staff, 1989 (Box 2)
  - State of the Graduate School address - Leo F. Solt, Dean, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Students, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Students completed third semester, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Tenure and promotion, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Thoren, Victor - obituary, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Three year reports, 1988-1990 (Box 2)
  - Thurman, Suzanne - visit, undated (Box 2)
  - University regulations and department rules, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - unknown items, undated (Box 2)
  - Van Egmond, Warren - Master's thesis proposal, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Visitors, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Winter, Nicholas - X600 outline, undated (Box 2)
  - X100, Fall 1989 (Box 2)
  - Ziemer, Bill, 1979 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1974-1990
  - A, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - B, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Blackwood, Timothy John, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - C, 1981; 1990 (Box 2)
  - Carmichael, Ann G., 1979; 1987 (Box 2)
  - Dunn, Michael, 1978 (Box 2)
  - E, 1978 (Box 2)
  - F, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Giere, Ronald, undated (Box 2)
  - Gordon, Michael V. W., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Gros-Louis, Kenneth R. R., 1979; 1990 (Box 2)
  - History of Science Society, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Horner, Jack, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Jennings, Carolyn, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Kintgen, Eugene, 1990 (Box 2)
  - L, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Lowengrub, Morton, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - Lowitt, Richard, 1978 (Box 2)
  - M, 1988; undated (Box 2)
  - Martin, Edwin A., 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Nastansky, Heinz-L., 1979 (Box 2)
  - O'Neil, Robert M., 1977-1979 (Box 2)
  - P-Q, 1988 (Box 2)
  - R, 1978; undated (Box 2)
  - S, 1977-1987 (Box 2)
  - Sageng, Erik, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Thayer, Terence K., 1989 (Box 2)
  - W, 1979; 1987 (Box 2)
  - Watson, Maxine, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Westfall, Richard, 1988 (Box 2)